It’s crazy when you think about all of
the different kinds of foods we eat.
We just swallow and hope
it all works out for the best.
Well, as it turns out,
there are better ways to think about keeping
our bodies humming healthfully along.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we look at how a plant-
based lifestyle is put to the test
against early and late-stage cancer.
Higher consumption of
a healthy plant-based diet
was significantly associated
with a lower chance
of having an elevated PSA,
which can be a sign
of prostate cancer.
We're talking about
potentially cutting the odds
of having an elevated PSA
in half with diet.
The researchers concluded:
"This study provides
strong evidence
supporting the potential use
of plant-based foods
in the prevention
and treatment
of prostate cancer."
"Not so fast", replied
an editor of the journal,
"This paper certainly
doesn't present final,
convincing proof
that reduced PSA levels
due to a plant-based diet
in fact translate
into what we actually care
about: less prostate cancer."
Harvard cohort researchers
took up the mantle
to answer that question.
And indeed,
greater consumption
of a healthful
plant-based diet does appear
to reduce the risk
of getting prostate cancer
and dying from prostate cancer
by nearly half
for men under age 65.
And those adhering more to a healthy
plant-based diet who do get cancer
had 90 percent lower odds
of ending up with high-grade,
more severe prostate cancer
and appeared to be better able
to handle cancer treatment
and ended up with
better sexual function,
less incontinence,
and more vitality.
This is consistent with the role
of diet and nutrition
in the prevention and treatment
of cancer more generally,
where the evidence points
to a diet
with minimal animal products.
What if you already
have cancer though?
Study findings suggest that
adhering to plant-based diets
may be beneficial
for overall cancer survival
and may potentially improve
the prognosis for common cancers
such as breast, colorectal,
and prostate cancers.
It starts with
case reports like this.
A 73-year-old man
with prostate cancer
was placed
on a plant-based diet,
and within 10 days,
his tumor markers were down
about 75 percent.
But case reports
are like glorified anecdotes.
You can't know
if a healthier diet
and lifestyle actually help
until you run a randomized,
controlled trial
and put it to the test.
Dr. Dean Ornish,
famous for showing
the progression of heart disease
could be reversed,
opening up arteries
without drugs,
without surgery,
just a plant-based diet
and lifestyle program,
eliminating angina chest pain
in about three-quarters
of patients
within a matter of months.
He decided to move
from killer #1— heart disease—
to killer #2—cancer.
93 men with early-stage
watch-and-wait prostate cancer
were randomized
to either standard care
or a plant-based diet along
with walking and relaxation.
The cancer tended to get worse
in the control group
but comparatively better
in the plant-based group.
When blood from the patients
on the standard diet
was dripped onto prostate cancer
cells growing in a petri dish,
cancer cell growth rates
were cut by 9 percent.
Their bodies were doing the best
they could to beat back the cancer.
The blood of patients on the
plant-based program, though,
knocked down the cancer
growth by 70 percent.
Eating and living
more healthfully
made their blood stream almost eight
times less hospitable to cancer.
Now, this was after a year.
Subsequent studies
have shown that you can see
a significant
cancer-fighting effect
after less than two weeks
on a similar Pritikin-style
plant-based diet with exercise.
Ornish took biopsies from
the prostate cancer patients
before and after three months
and saw a significant change
in the expression
of more than 500 genes.
Of course,
what we really care about
are disease outcomes.
By the two-year follow-up,
significantly more men
in the control group
had enough cancer progression
that they had to go
into treatment, for example,
five had to get
radical prostatectomies,
which can lead
to urinary incontinence
and impotence in 60 percent,
whereas none of the men
in the lifestyle group
were forced to go into surgery.
What about those
with more serious disease?
Researchers followed 10 patients
with recurrent prostate cancer,
meaning those whose
invasive cancer had to be cut
or burned out with radiation,
yet their PSA levels
started to rise again,
signaling the cancer was back.
There was no control group
per se in this study.
Each patient was
kind of their own control
before and after,
being asked to center
their diets around
more whole plant foods.
There was a significant decrease
in the rate of PSA rise,
suggesting a slowing
of cancer growth.
4 out of 10 patients
actually saw their PSA levels
go down,
suggesting the possibility
of at least some degree
of disease remission.
9 out of 10 had a reduction
in their rates of PSA rise
as well as an improvement
of their PSA doubling times,
which is a proxy for how fast
the tumor doubles in size.
The increase
in average doubling time
went from about 12 months
before the dietary change
to 112 months,
which is the largest that has
ever been reported in any kind
of dietary intervention trial
for recurrent prostate cancer.
What about
really advanced cancer,
stage four with spread
to distant organs?
Out of nine patients
willing to go on
a plant-based
macrobiotic diet,
three men experienced
long-term regression
of multiple
bone lesions,
compared to no regression
or healing
in nine matched
control subjects
who continued eating
the standard American diet.
Those on the healthier diet
went on to live
an average of 19 years more,
compared to those with
the same severity of cancer
not even living
for 4 years more, on average,
on their standard diet.
Now this was not
a randomized study,
so maybe it says something
about those
willing to eat healthfully
rather than
healthful eating itself.
But what's the downside?
As Dr. Ornish likes to say,
"The only side effects
are good ones."
A large number of patients
with metastatic prostate cancer,
for example,
die not from their cancer,
but rather
from non-cancer causes,
and the number one cause
is heart disease,
so, a heart-healthy diet
could only help.
Dr. Dean Ornish showed that a plant-
based diet and lifestyle program
could apparently reverse the
progression of prostate cancer
by making men’s bloodstream nearly 8 times
better at suppressing cancer cell growth,
but this was for early stage, localized,
watch-and-wait prostate cancer.
What about for more advanced
stage life-threatening disease?
There had been sporadic case reports
in the literature suggestive of benefit.
A man, for example, with
extensive metastatic disease,
given maybe three years to live,
goes on a strict plant-based diet.
Four years later, it appears
the cancer has disappeared.
Six years in, he gets a little cocky
and backslides a little bit on the diet.
Cancer comes raging
back and he dies.
But, that could have been
a total coincidence.
That’s the problem with case reports,
which are just kind of glorified anecdotes—
you have no idea how representative the
outcome is unless it’s formally studied.
But throughout the 20th century, all we had
were these kinds of case reports... until 2001.
So, we had this preliminary evidence
based on all the case reports
that prostate cancer may be sensitive
to diet even after it metastasizes,
may prolong survival
and even cause remission
of bone metastases in men
with advanced disease.
So, researchers decided to put it to
the test, 4-month intervention.
They figured too much saturated fat,
too little fiber, and too much meat
may be the biggest players in
tumor promotion and progression.
So, they put people on a
whole food plant-based diet
of whole grains, beans,
seeds, and fruit.
Figuring this would be quite the
departure from their regular diet,
they included a stress reduction component
in hopes of improving dietary compliance.
Okay so, who were
these ten men?
They all didn’t just
have prostate cancer;
they all had underwent a radical
prostatectomy to remove their primary tumor,
and then subsequently
had increasing PSA levels,
indicative of probable
metastatic disease.
PSA stands for prostate-specific antigen;
it’s only made by prostate cells,
and they just had their
entire prostates removed.
So the level
should be zero.
The fact that they not
only still had some PSA,
but that it was rising suggests
that the surgery failed,
and the cancer had spread
and was making a comeback.
The cancer would presumably still be powering
away and spreading just as fast as before.
Instead, this happened.
In two men, it looks like the cancer
accelerated, grew even faster,
but in the other 8 men, the
intervention appeared to work,
apparently slowing
down cancer growth,
and in three it didn’t
just slow or stop,
but appeared to
reverse and shrink.
Why the different
responses?
Well, in the Ornish study,
the more people complied
with the diet and lifestyle
recommendations, the better they did.
Dietary changes only work
if you actually do them.
Just because you tell people to start
eating a whole food plant-based diet,
doesn’t mean patients
actually do it.
One can use fiber intake as a
proxy for dietary compliance,
since all whole plant
foods have fiber,
and Ornish’s patients about doubled
their fiber intake from 31 to 59.
How did this group do?
They started out even worse,
averaging 14 grams a day,
and only made it up
to 19 grams a day.
That’s not a whole
food plant-based diet—
that doesn’t even make it up to
the recommended minimum daily intake.
If you look closely, only 4 men
increased their fiber intake at all.
So maybe that may explain
the different responses.
Like, how did
patient 2 do?
The man whose fiber improved the
most had the best PSA result,
and the man whose fiber intake dropped
the most had the worst PSA result.
And indeed, it appears the
more change they made
to their diet, the
better their results.
The researchers concluded that
a plant-based diet delivered
in the context of stress management
may slow the rate of tumor progression,
and unlike other treatments, may give
patients some control over their disease.
And, as Ornish
pointed out,
“the only side effects
are beneficial ones.”
Finally today,
we look at what happens when
metastatic prostate cancer patients
were taught to increase intake of
whole grains, vegetables, fruits, and beans,
and to decrease consumption
of meat, dairy, and junk.
Dr. Ornish and colleagues were
able to show an apparent reversal
in the progression of early
stage localized prostate cancer
with a plant-based diet
and lifestyle program,
and researchers at the University of Massachusetts
and elsewhere showed a similar diet
may help slow the progression of even advanced
prostate cancer over a period of four months.
How about six months?
Researchers at UC San Diego found more
cancer patients in the same situation
and put them through
the same protocol.
These were patients who were already
treated for invasive prostate cancer
by either radical prostatectomy
or radiation therapy,
yet had rising PSA levels suggesting
the treatment didn’t work,
and the cancer
was on the move.
In those with a cancer recurrence,
PSA levels typically rise exponentially,
reflecting the gradual, inexorable
growth of the cancer in the body.
The rate of this PSA rise
is the single best predictor
of the development of overt metastatic
disease, as well as of overall survival.
The next step would be what’s
called hormonal therapy,
which is chemical or surgical castration,
which has a list of side effects,
including loss of libido and sexual
function and strength and vitality.
Therefore, we try to hold off
on that for as long as possible;
so, if we’re just waiting, we
might as well give diet a try.
So, they were taught to increase intake
of whole grains, vegetables, fruit, and beans
and to decrease meat,
dairy, and refined carbs.
Of all possible lifestyle interventions,
why a whole food plant-based diet?
Well, if you look around the
world, there are
huge differences in
prostate cancer rates,
with “We’re #1 USA, USA”
rates up to a hundred times
higher than some places
in Asia, for example.
And, it’s not just genetic; within one
generation of coming to the U.S.,
cancer rates shoot up, and the grandkids
end up with the same top-of-the-pile rates.
A whole range of lifestyle
factors have been looked at,
but diet appears to have
the greatest influence.
Specifically, consumption of meat
and dairy appears to increase risk,
and consumption of plant foods
appears to decrease risk;
hence, the plant-based diet.
A possible mechanism is arachidonic
acid, an inflammatory compound
which we make from omega-6 rich oils like
corn, sunflower, safflower, and cottonseed,
and also comes preformed
in animal-based foods,
particularly in chicken in the
American diet, and also eggs.
And, in a petri dish, at least,
arachidonic acid appears to stimulate
prostate cancer cell
growth as much 200%.
But, ask men to remove processed
and animal foods from their diet
for six months and
what happens?
9 of the 10 patients showed an
apparent slowing of cancer growth,
and 4 of the 9 an apparent
reversal in cancer growth.
The average doubling time, an
estimate of how long it takes
for their cancer
to double in size,
slowed from doubling every year
to closer to every 10 years.
There’s been other studies using various
diets and nutritional interventions,
like vitamin supplements, but none
have worked as well as this one.
And their compliance wasn’t
even all that great.
They did good about boosting
their whole grain consumption,
especially in those first three
months, but then backslid a bit.
They did eat more vegetables,
including a serving
of greens and an extra serving
of fruit, at least early on,
and at least ate one whole serving
of legumes a day, when they started.
So, the researchers did observe some dietary
recidivism by the end of the study.
The patients started out stronger, but then
started to slide back into old habits.
So, the researchers checked
to see if maybe they were better
able to beat off the disease
during that earlier period,
and indeed, at the end of three months,
on average, there was PSA reversal.
So, changes in the rate of PSA rise were like
opposite that of whole plant food intake,
raising the provocative possibility that
PSA may have been tracking those changes
suggesting that the adoption of a plant-based
diet may have therapeutic potential
in the management of
recurrent prostate cancer.
Their findings suggest that without
further surgery, radiation, or chemo,
disease progression can be
slowed or even reversed,
despite the “prevailing
scientific consensus
that cancer progression
is largely irreversible.”
They're not refuting the
benefits of standard therapies
and not guaranteeing that a plant-based
diet and stress reduction
will always
induce remission.
But, the results do contribute to
this growing medical literature
that in at least some circumstances,
cancer may be partly reversible.
Just by modifying dietary and lifestyle factors,
men may be able to prevent disease spread,
all without getting their
testicles chopped off.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
As always, all proceeds from
book sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.